Guide to the Agnes Rindge Claflin Papers, circa 1901 - circa 1977
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Agnes Rindge Claflin Papers
circa 1901 - circa 1977
1927-1934
Claflin, Agnes Rindge, 1900-1977
3.3 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The bulk of the Claflin collection is from the years 1927-1934, the period in which she received her graduate degrees and began to teach at Vassar College as an associate professor and later as a full professor. While the collection itself is mainly made up of correspondence, it also contains an eclectic selection of material, including: various drafts of her doctoral thesis, newspaper clippings concerning her career, programs of exhibits, class notes and assorted miscellanea.
Biographical Note
Agnes Millicent Rindge was born on May 19, 1900 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. Upon graduating the Madeira School in 1917, she attended Mount Holyoke College for two years, and in 1921, having being elected to Phi Beta Kappa, received her B.A. magna cum laude from Radcliffe College. In 1923, Rindge joined the faculty of the Vassar Art Department as an instructor. She returned to Radcliffe to do graduate work, receiving her M.A. in 1927 and her Ph.D. in 1928. In the fall of that year, Rindge rejoined the Vassar Art Department as an associate professor. After three years, she was promoted to the rank of full professor. Rindge was director of the Vassar Art Gallery (1943-1962), Chairperson of the Art Department (1943-1965), and Mary Conover Mellon Professor of Art (1961-1965).
Her most extensive written work is Sculpture which was published in 1929. Subsequently, she wrote The Elder Pieter Bruegel: A Short Essay (1936), as well as numerous articles for publications such as International Studio, Parnassus, and Formes.
Over the course of several decades, Rindge lectured at many of this country's foremost institutions of higher learning, including: New York University Institute of Fine Arts, Chicago Art Institute, Wadsworth Athenaeum, Columbia University, Yale School of Fine Art, and at other universities too many to enumerate.
During World War II, Rindge served as Executive Secretary and Consultant in the Art Division of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (1941-1942), and continued as Consultant in the Program of Cultural Relations with Latin America, where she was concerned with the circulation and exposure of Latin American Art within the United States.
At approximately the same time, she became a member of the Advisory Committee of the Museum of Modern Art (1944), and served as Assistant Executive Vice President of the Museum (1943-44). In connection with a Calder Sculpture exhibition held at the Museum of Modern Art, she wrote and narrated a film entitled Alexander Calder: Sculpture and Constructions.
Rindge was active in many art organizations, including membership in the Commission on Arts of the American Association of Colleges (1939), Chairperson of the Committee on Fellowships of the College Art Association (1945-1948), member of the Editorial Board of Art in America (1940-1943), as well as President of the American Federation of Arts (1944-1945).
Her associates included Alfred Barr, founder of the Museum of Modern Art, A. Everett Austin, head of the Wadsworth Athenaeum, as well as artists such as Alexander Calder, Eugene Berman and Pavel Tchelitchew.
Rindge was noted for her colorful manner of dress and for having, as one former student and later colleague put it, a "verbal wit and playfulness that so often outran pedestrian minds." Yet Rindge was also known not to accept less than what she felt a person capable of -- "She had expectations, and when they were fulfilled she was encouraging; when they were not, one felt one had placed more than oneself in jeopardy."*
In 1945, Miss Rindge married Philip W. Claflin, a captain in the U.S. Army. Mrs. Claflin was awarded an honorary degree of Doctor of Letters from Wheaton College in 1962, and a year later received the Graduate Society Medal from Radcliffe College. She died on June 12, 1977, at the age of seventy-seven.
*Quotations from Pamela Askew, Bulletin of the Vassar Art Gallery, Claflin collection, Box 6, Folder 93.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the Claflin collection is from the years 1927-1934, the period in which she received her graduate degrees and began to teach at Vassar College as an associate professor and later as a full professor. While the collection itself is mainly made up of correspondence, it also contains an eclectic selection of material, including: various drafts of her doctoral thesis, newspaper clippings concerning her career, programs of exhibits, class notes and assorted miscellanea.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Pamela Askew Papers
Vassar College Art Department Records
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Art--Study and teaching; Women college teachers
Document Types:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Financial records; Photographs; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Family; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, January 2009. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, February 2024.
Acquisition Information
Photocopies of correspondence between A. Everett Austin, Jr., et al. and Claflin, were the gift of the Wadsworth Athenaeum, Hartford, CT, April 1991.
The class notes, postcards, and photos in boxes 3 and 4 were donated by Christina Houghtaling, VC 1974, in October 2015. Ms. Houghtaling rescued the material from a dumpster on or near campus some time after Claflin's death. [M2016-001]
Teaching materials and correspondence were transferred from the Vassar College Art Department, 2016. [M2019-034]
Baby photograph of Agnes Rindge Claflin in Folder 154 was the gift of Julian Rebelo, February 2024. [M2024-005]
The source of the rest of the collection is unknown, although some material was likely transferred from the Art Department, circa 1977-1981.
Series List
- Series I. Personal Material, 1910-1935; (Box 1)
  This series includes correspondence with parents, letters to relatives and childhood friends, as well as information on her wedding and the death of her mother, Miriam Rindge.
- Series II. Professional Material, (Box 1); 1929-1963
  This series consists of material related to Claflin's professional activities outside of Vassar College.
- Series III. Harvard University, 1926-1932; (Box 1)
  This series includes Claflin's correspondence with Harvard professors and personnel, as well as class notes and several versions of her published doctoral thesis, Sculpture.
- Series IV. Vassar College, undated; (Boxes 1-2)
  This series contains correspondence with faculty, alumnae and students and official faculty memorandums among other things.
- Series V. Financial papers, 1928-1936; (Box 2)
  The three boxes of this series contain personal bills, letters concerning salary, canceled checks and bank statements.
- Series VI. General Material, circa 1901-1934; (Boxes 2-4)
  This series is, for the most part, a "catch all" category; many of Claflin's friends were also her colleagues and vice versa -- many items which could not realistically fit into the aforementioned groups were placed here. Much in the way of personal and professional correspondence that did not meet the guidelines of the overall scheme have been arranged alphabetically in the General Material series. Also included:Index cards with photographs, organized by subject, and miscellaneous post cards and photographs of actors (M2016-001).
- Series VII. Addition: M2019-034, 1929 - circa 1977; (Box 5)
  Correspondence, teaching materials, and printed material related to Claflin's work in the Vassar College Art Department.
Container List
- PERSONAL MATERIAL
  - General
    - Greeting cards, invitations, Christmas cards, (24 items) (Folder 1.1)
    - Letters from childhood friends, 1910-1912; (27 items) (Folder 1.2)
    - Letters from childhood friends, 1925-1935; (12 items) (Folder 1.3)
    - Letters from Sally H. Dunn, childhood friend, (4 items) (Folder 1.4)
    - Death of Miriam Rindge, mother, (4 letters, 1 newspaper clipping) (Folder 1.5)
    - Wedding of Agnes and Philip Claflin, (1 invitation, 4 newspaper clippings) (Folder 1.6)
  - Correspondence with relatives
    - Correspondence with relatives, (14 items) (Folder 1.7)
    - Correspondence with Ruth Harter, aunt, (8 letters, 4 poems) (Folder 1.8)
    - Letters from Miriam Rindge to Ruth Harter, (3 letters) (Folder 1.9)
  - Travel
    - European travel arrangements, 1932; (4 items) (Folder 1.10)
    - Maps, schedules, ship information, (3 maps, 1 log abstract, 1 train schedule) (Folder 1.11)
  - Personal Miscellanea
    - Miscellaneous items, (30 items including poems, limericks, and newspaper clippings) (Folder 1.12)
  - Letters from parents
    - Rindge, Harry, 1911, 1928-1929; (14 letters) (Folder 1.13)
    - Rindge, Harry, 1930-1932; (25 letters) (Folder 1.14)
    - Rindge, Miriam, 1928; (13 letters) (Folder 1.15)
    - Rindge, Miriam, 1929-1932; (6 letters) (Folder 1.16)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (16 letters) (Folder 1.17)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (10 letters) (Folder 1.18)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (15 letters) (Folder 1.19)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (9 letters) (Folder 1.20)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (10 letters) (Folder 1.21)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (9 letters) (Folder 1.22)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (4 letters) (Folder 1.23)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (9 letters) (Folder 1.24)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (10 letters) (Folder 1.25)
    - Rindge, Miriam, undated; (7 letters) (Folder 1.26)
- PROFESSIONAL MATERIAL
  - College Art Association American Institute for Persian Art and Archaeology, (15 items) (Folder 1.27)
  - Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies of the Archaeological Institute of America, (12 items) (Folder 1.28)
  - Advisory Committee for Scholarship Grants in the Fine Arts of the Carnegie Corporation, (12 items) (Folder 1.29)
  - National Soap Sculpture Committee, (13 items) (Folder 1.30)
  - Lectures given, (7 items) (Folder 1.31)
  - Announcements, gallery and exhibit openings, (14 items) (Folder 1.32)
  - Miscellaneous professional correspondence: Abbot – McMahon, (37 items) (Folder 1.33)
  - Miscellaneous professional correspondence: Pope – Richard, (12 items) (Folder 1.34)
  - Newspaper clippings on Claflin's career, 1929-1963; (20 clippings) (Folder 1.35)
  - Miscellaneous professional material(includes guide to Warburg Institute of London, listing Guggenheim Fellowships for 1933, copy of Art in America, (10 items) (Folder 1.36)
- HARVARD UNIVERSITY
  - Ph.D. Thesis
    - Outlines of work, (4 items) (Folder 1.37)
    - Preface, Bibliography, Summary, (2 items) (Folder 1.38)
    - Introduction, "The Nature and Function of Sculpture" pp. xv - 12, Sculpture (Folder 1.39)
    - "Requirements of Sculpture as an Art Form" pp.15 - 32, Sculpture (Folder 1.40)
    - "The Origin and Purpose of Sculpture" pp. 33 - 50, Sculpture (Folder 1.41)
    - "Analysis of Grand Periods of Sculpture"(Romanesque) pp. 53 - 82, Sculpture (Folder 1.42)
    - "Analysis.. ." (incomplete 2nd version) pp. 56 - 82, Sculpture (Folder 1.43)
    - "Further Analysis of Grand Periods of Sculpture"(incomplete) pp. 83 - 96, Sculpture (Folder 1.44)
    - "Realism" pp. 99 - 139, Sculpture (Folder 1.45)
    - "Realism" (incomplete 2nd version) pp. 99 - 117, Sculpture (Folder 1.46)
    - "The Contemporary Creed" pp. 143 - 184, Sculpture (Folder 1.47)
    - "The Contemporary Creed" (incomplete 2nd version) pp. 155 - 184, Sculpture (Folder 1.48)
    - Sculpture, Various loose pages (Folder 1.49)
    - Footnotes, edited material (Folder 1.50)
    - Rough notes (Folder 1.51)
  - Letters of Reference
    - Letters of introduction from Dr. Paul Sachs, B - K, (9 letters) (Folder 1.52)
    - Letters of introduction from Dr. Paul Sachs, L - W, (8 letters) (Folder 1.53)
    - Professional cards of introduction from Dr. Paul Sachs, (41 cards) (Folder 1.54)
  - Harvard Correspondence
    - C-M, (19 items) (Folder 1.55)
    - P-S, (24 items) (Folder 1.56)
  - Miscellanea
    - Harvard Co-op date book, 1927 (Folder 1.57)
    - Report Card, 1926-1927 (Folder 1.57)
    - Application for Radcliffe commencement, 1932 (Folder 1.57)
    - Ballot for Radcliffe alumnae election (Folder 1.57)
    - Program of Radcliffe graduation (Folder 1.57)
  - Class Notes
    - Ancient Art (Folder 1.58)
    - Ancient Painting (Folder 1.59)
    - Dutch Painting in the 17th Century (Folder 1.60)
    - Economic Theory (Folder 1.61)
    - Fine Arts 9a, vol. I (Folder 1.62)
    - Fine Arts 9a, vol. II (Folder 1.63)
    - Fine Arts 9a, vol. III (Folder 1.64)
    - French notes on Medieval Art (Folder 1.65)
    - French Painting (Folder 1.66)
    - [Greco-Roman Art I] (Folder 1.67)
    - [Greco-roman Art II] (Folder 1.68)
    - Hellenistic and Greco-Roman Sculpture (Folder 1.69)
    - Intellectual History of Medieval Europe (Folder 1.70)
    - Medieval Manuscripts (Folder 1.71)
    - Medieval Sculpture (Folder 1.72)
    - Modes of Painting Oriental Art Miscellanea (Folder 1.73)
    - Monastic Art I (Folder 1.74)
    - Monastic Art II (Folder 1.74a)
    - Renaissance History I (Folder 1.74b)
    - Renaissance History II (Folder 1.74c)
    - Roman Painting (Folder 1.74d)
    - Romanesque Architecture (Folder 1.74e)
    - Romanesque Historical Survey (Folder 1.74f)
    - Romanesque >Sculpture I (Folder 1.74g)
    - Romanesque Sculpture II (Folder 1.74h)
    - Spanish Painting (Folder 1.74i)
    - Technical Aspects of Art (Folder 1.74j)
    - [Unidentified, written in French] (Folder 1.74k)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 1.74l)
    - Syllabus for Art Outline B (Folder 1.74m)
    - Syllabus for Fine Arts Ic (Folder 1.74n)
    - [Reproduction of Art Slides I] (Folder 1.74o)
    - [Reproduction of Art Slides II] (Folder 1.74p)
- VASSAR COLLEGE
  - Correspondence with Alumnae
    - Adelaide (last name unknown), (7 letters, 5 photographs) (Folder 1.74q)
    - Alter, (18 items, including 5 newspaper clippings) (Folder 1.75)
    - Berstein - Kelly, (18 letters) (Folder 1.76)
    - Kohn, (17 letters) (Folder 1.77)
    - Louchheim - Miller, (12 letters) (Folder 1.78)
    - Rombauer - Wilson, (33 letters (1 unidentified)) (Folder 1.79)
  - Faculty Correspondence
    - Barber, Leila, (16 items) (Folder 2.80)
    - Borden - Gould, (13 items) (Folder 2.81)
    - MacCracken, Henry Noble, (13 items) (Folder 2.82)
    - Lamson - Tonks, (14 items) (Folder 2.83)
  - Student Correspondence
    - Correspondence with VC students, (13 letters) (Folder 2.84)
    - Letters of Recommendation for VC students — general, (16 letters) (Folder 2.85)
    - Letters of Recommendation for VC students — to Vassar Committee on Fellowships, (7 letters) (Folder 2.86)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Art department and Claflin, (5 clippings) (Folder 2.87)
  - Lectures
    - Speakers at Vassar, (13 items) (Folder 2.88)
    - Lectures given at Vassar Clubs, (8 items) (Folder 2.89)
  - Memorandums
    - Faculty memorandums, (12 memorandums) (Folder 2.90)
  - Retirement
    - Publicity plans of Vassar News Office, (12 items) (Folder 2.91)
    - Claflin exhibition, (9 clippings & programs) (Folder 2.92)
  - Death
    - Vassar press release, Bulletin of Art Gallery in memory of Claflin, (4 items, 2 obituaries) (Folder 2.93)
    - Program of exhibition in Claflin's memory, (2 items) (Folder 2.94)
  - Miscellanea
    - Miscellaneous items, (20 items, letters, poems and slide info.) (Folder 2.95)
- FINANCIAL PAPERS
  - Grand Rapids Trust Company
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 1 Jan 1928 - 1 July 1928; (4 items) (Folder 2.96)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 6 June 1928 - 1 Jan 1929; (2 items) (Folder 2.97)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 6 Dec 1928 - 1 July 1929; (2 items) (Folder 2.98)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 6 June 1929 - 1 Jan 1929; (3 items) (Folder 2.99)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 6 Dec 1929 - 28 July 1930; (4 items) (Folder 2.100)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 7 June 1930 - 4 June 1931, undated; (8 items) (Folder 2.101)
  - Personal Bills
    - Abercrombie & Fitch-Best Co., 1929-1931; (33 items) (Folder 2.102)
    - Blue Ribbon Dyeing and Cleaning Co. - Franklin & Simon Co., 1928-1931; (42 items) (Folder 2.103)
    - Hawes Inc. - Luckey, Platt & Co., 1929-1931; (48 items) (Folder 2.104)
    - Mack and Frey - Radcliffe Alumnae Fund, 1929-1931; (35 items) (Folder 2.105)
    - Robert Hamilton - Zimmer Brothers, foreign and unidentified bills, (39 items) (Folder 2.106)
  - Western Reserve University
    - Job Offer, (20 items) (Folder 2.107)
  - Vassar College
    - Appointment and Letters Concerning Salary, (13 items) (Folder 2.108)
    - Personal Bills, (67 items) (Folder 2.109)
  - Vassar Bank
    - Checking statements, canceled checks, Nov-Dec 1928 (Folder 2.110)
    - Checking statements, canceled checks, Jan-Apr 1929 (Folder 2.111)
    - Bankbook, Sept. 1928-June 1929 (Folder 2.112)
    - Bankbook, Oct. 1929-May 1930 (Folder 2.113)
    - Bankbook, May-Dec 1930 (Folder 2.114)
    - Checking statements, canceled checks, Dec. 1930-Mar. 1931 (Folder 2.115)
    - Checking statements, canceled checks, Apr-May1931 (Folder 2.116)
    - Bankbook, Dec. 1930-Oct. 1931 (Folder 2.117)
    - Bankbook, Oct. 1931-Nov. 1932 (Folder 2.118)
    - Bankbook, Nov-Dec 1932 (Folder 2.119)
    - Bankbook, Jan-Dec 1933 (Folder 2.120)
    - Bankbook, Jan-Oct 1934 (Folder 2.121)
    - Checking statements, canceled checks, Aug-Sept 1935 (Folder 2.122)
    - Bankbook, Oct. 1934-May 1936 (Folder 2.123)
    - Bankbook, Oct. 1935-May 1936 (Folder 2.124)
    - Receipts, various bank material (Folder 2.125)
  - Miscellanea
    - Miscellaneous materials, including checkbooks, taxation letter, (14 items) (Folder 2.126)
- GENERAL MATERIAL
  - Correspondence
    - Askew, Constance, undated; (2 letters) (Folder 2.127)
    - [Askew], Kirk, (11 letters) (Folder 2.127a)
    - A - B, (34 letters) (Folder 2.128)
    - Brewer, Joseph, 1926-1932; (15 letters) (Folder 2.129)
    - Brewer, Joseph, 1933-1934, undated; (13 letters) (Folder 2.130)
    - Burrage, Francis, 1927-1931; (19 letters) (Folder 2.131)
    - Burrage, Francis, undated; (21 letters) (Folder 2.132)
    - Choate, Nat, 1927-1931; (20 letters) (Folder 2.133)
    - C - E, (22 letters) (Folder 2.134)
    - F, (29 letters) (Folder 2.135)
    - Gordon, Douglas, 1928-1930; (19 letters) (Folder 2.136)
    - Gordon, Douglas, 1931-1934; (20 letters) (Folder 2.137)
    - G - I, (20 letters) (Folder 2.138)
    - J, (16 letters) (Folder 2.139)
    - K - M, (43 letters) (Folder 2.141)
    - Norton, W.W., (11 letters) (Folder 2.142)
    - Porter, Alan, 1933-1934; (5 letters) (Folder 2.143)
    - Porter, Alan, undated; (6 letters) (Folder 2.144)
    - Rowland, Ben, (12 letters) (Folder 2.145)
    - O - Sa, (29 letters) (Folder 2.146)
    - So - T, (24 letters) (Folder 2.147)
    - Wheeler, Dinsmore, 1928-1930; (7 letters) (Folder 2.148)
    - Wheeler, Dinsmore, 1930-1933; (4 letters) (Folder 2.149)
    - Wheeler, Dinsmore, undated; (10 letters) (Folder 2.150)
    - W, (17 letters) (Folder 2.151)
    - Unidentified, (25 items) (Folder 2.152)
  - Olivet College
    - Joseph Brewer Address, (1 item) (Folder 2.153)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Claflin, circa 1901, undated; (3 photographs) (Folder 2.154)
  - Wadsworth Athenaeum
    - Photocopies of correspondence from A. Everett Austin, Jr., et al. and Claflin, [may not be photocopied or quoted without permission from Wadsworth Athenaeum] (Folder 2.155)
  - Rouault Poster
    - Poster of a Georges Rouault painting given to a friend (Mapcase)
  - M2016-001
    - Miscellaneous post cards and photographs of actors (Box 3)
    - Index cards with photographs, organized by subject (Box 4)
- Addition: M2019-034
  - Correspondence, teaching materials, and printed materials, 1929 - circa 1977; [unprocessed] (Box 5)